Let us talk about prairie analysis and posterior testing. These are the two terms that are used
for algorithms and the programs. Prairie analysis is done over the algorithm. So,
prairie analysis means we will do the analysis of an algorithm by studying it into greater
detail knowing how it is working and we get some results. The result of analysis there.
What is that? We may find out the time and the space consumed by an algorithm.
The result of analysis and testing is done on the program. So, we run and execute the program and
check it. So, we will know the wash time it is taking, how much, how many seconds,
milliseconds it is taking and also the amount of memory it is consuming in terms of bytes.
So, this is prairie analysis is done on algorithm and the posterior testing is done on programs.
Now, when prairie analysis is done over an algorithm, we know that algorithms are not
written in a particular language. So, they are language independent and also
they are hardware independent. They are not meant for a particular hardware.
But if it has a program, we write it program that is hardware specific as well as language
specific and as well as operating system specific, environment specific also. So,
they are dependent on the hardware as well as the programming language used.
And here the result of this one is how we get the time and the space.
We don't get wash time 3 minutes, 10 minutes, 5 seconds or milliseconds. No,
we will get the time function and we get the space function.