Now next video, characteristics of algorithm. What are the characteristics?
What are the properties of an algorithm? So let us check. First one, algorithm
must take some input. So algorithm, some algorithm may not take any input also
but algorithm can take zero or more input. They can take zero or more input.
The next, output. Algorithm must generate at least one output otherwise it's no
use of writing algorithm. It must generate some result. See imagine them
like a function, C language function. Like when you call a function, function
may not take any parameters also but function returns something. If it's not
returning we say void but it does something definitely. If it is
return type like but the function gives some result definitely. That's what is
the output. At least one output. Then definiteness. Every statement should be
unambiguous and it should have a single and exact meaning. You cannot write any
statement which cannot be understood or which cannot be solved. Like if the
human cannot solve it, we can't ask our computers to solve that one. So every
statement that you're writing should be definite. That's clear. So definiteness.
You cannot use the value. For example I tell you, you cannot use the value
that suppose root minus one. It's unknown value. Unknown value. So we say it as
imaginary number. So you cannot treat it as a real number and in the
algorithm. Right? This is an example I'm giving you. So every statement must give clear meaning.
Only one meaning. That's it. Then next is finiteness. Algorithm is just like a
function as I said. A function will have some limited set of steps and it
will stop and returns the result. So same way algorithm must terminate at
some point. Whether it may be having 10 statements or maybe having 10,000
statement but it must have finite set of statement. The duration of algorithm
must be finite. Definitely we'll stop writing after some statements you may
stop. But the meaning here is that there are some programs which runs
continuously unless and until you stop them. Like example database server.
Oracle server you start and if you leave the machine as it is and don't
stop it then Oracle server will be keep on running. SQL server it will be keep on
running. It's like a service. Web server keep on running. So it is not a service.
It's an algorithm. It's a procedure. So it must stop. Then effectiveness. Now this is
simple. You should not write unnecessary statements in an algorithm.
Whatever the statement you write the objective is that it should do
something, serve some purpose in the procedure in the steps of an algorithm.
Don't write unnecessary statements. See algorithm is like a procedure. So there are
many procedure. Like a chemistry experiment done by the students in the
laboratory is a procedure. And physics experiment done by the students in the
laboratory is also procedure. Or if you take a procedure for preparing a dish,
cooking a dish that is a recipe that's also procedure. And every procedure the
names I have given you, examples I have given you, every procedure needs some
input. Like chemical experiment needs some chemicals and the apparatus and
physics experiment needs in instruments and the recipe needs some
ingredients. Then objective of that procedure is to give some result. You
are cooking and cooking but no dish is prepared. Nothing like that. You are
doing some experiment but no solution is obtained in chemistry experiment. No
there must be some solution. So definitely there must be some solution. At least one
solution. Definiteness. All the steps that you are doing are known step only.
You are not doing anything magical. Right? Known steps you are performing.
Every step that you are doing here is known step and it's nothing is
magical. Right? Only known steps you are performing. And finiteness. If you are
preparing a dish you will stop at some point and the dish is ready. If
you are doing a chemical experiment you will stop at some point and the
solution is ready. Definitely. And effectiveness. Effectiveness. You will
not do anything unnecessary while doing this procedure. Like you are
boiling some chemical and but you're not using it in the experiment. It's
not mixed with the solution. You are cutting some vegetables in the recipe
but that is not used in the dish. So there is unnecessary things are not
done in the procedure. So here also in the algorithm you should not have any
unnecessary statements.