Next, let us see how to write an algorithm. Here already I have written one algorithm
for swapping two numbers or two elements. See, I have used C language like syntax only.
Only the thing I have done is here I wrote algorithm to show that okay I am writing
an algorithm, it's not a program. Here, if I compare with a C program, here I have
not written the data type of parameters. Yes, data types we don't decide at algorithm
time. When we write a program, then we decide what data types are required.
And here, even I don't have a temporary variable declaration. Declaration is not there. Directly
it is used. It's understood. Unless you declare in the program, you cannot use it.
But in an algorithm, we don't bother about those minor things that are related to language.
This is more like C. Now if you want to write in a different way, you can say this as
begin and this as end. Instead of lower brackets, you can also say begin and end.
Next, you can use this symbol also for assignment. Actually, this is an assignment
symbol that was used in some old languages like Pascal language. So you can use that one.
Or else, you can use this symbol for showing that this value is stored at this one.
So now it's up to you how you want to write it. I hope whatever I wrote, you have understood
it. So same way, whatever you write, I should be able to understand, at least you should be able
to understand it. Or the people who are involved in the project should be able to understand it.
People who are using it should be able to understand it.
Right? So you can use any syntax. There is no fixed syntax for writing any algorithm.
Let's see how to analyze an algorithm. What is the criteria on which we analyze an algorithm?
So the criteria is, the first criteria is time.
See the algorithms are the procedures for solving problem. Whether you do it manually using pen and
paper or you make a program and let your machines do it. Whatever the method may be,
how much time it is taking. If the procedure is very lengthy and time consuming or whether
the procedure is very fast and quickly you can get the results. So that is one of the
important criteria on which we have to analyze. If you are devising a procedure or an algorithm,
then it should be time efficient. Means it must be faster. So after writing the algorithms,
we analyze how much time it is taking. So that time what we get is in the time in the form of a
function. We get a function, time function. We not get the watch time already I have shown you.
You will get the function, time function. Now next is space.
As the algorithm is going to be converted into a program and it's going to run on the machine,
then we need to know how much memory space it will consume. So that is the second criteria on
which we will analyze an algorithm. So these are the two major criteria on which the algorithms
are analyzed. And furthermore if you have any other criteria and furthermore if you have
any other criteria or any other factors you want to consider, you can consider them like.
Now,
nowadays every application is either internet based or web based or say cloud based. So data
transfer or network consumption is also an important criteria. How much data is going
to be transferred? See if the algorithm or means if a procedure that you're writing,
if it's unnecessary transferring to larger size data or it can be reduced or compressed,
whatever it is. So that is one more important criteria that is how much data transfer is done.
And nowadays most of the devices are handheld instead of PCs we are using
pound drops and laptops and tablets. Then power consumption is also a criteria.
How much power it is consuming?
And one more criteria is if you are developing an algorithm for device drivers or system level
programming, if you are developing something, some algorithm if you are writing, then
you may also need to know how much CPU registers it is consuming.
So CPU will also have some memory called as registers. How many registers it is consuming?
That's also one of the worrying factor when you are designing an algorithm or writing a program
family. So these are a few criterias I have listed and it depends on your requirement,
it depends on your project, right? What are the more criterias you need to analyze?
Now let us see, I have taken one example to show you how we analyze an algorithm.
So for analysis purpose, we need to know the time. So first we'll do time analysis.
Then we'll do space analysis. Now time means how much time this will take?
This is not the watch time. Then how to assume? Now we say that
every statement in an algorithm takes one unit of time. Every simple statement
in an algorithm takes one unit of time. If suppose the algorithm is calling another algorithm,
it's using another procedure, then we have to analyze that also in detail.
So simple means just a statement, it's not a nested statement, right? So single statement,
each statement takes one unit of time. So here I assume it takes one unit of time,
one unit of time, one unit. So total time is three. So the time function
f of n is three. Here we got the constant value because I have taken a very simple algorithm
and the answer is three, that is some constant value, right? Three or thirty, whatever it is,
it is constant value, fixed value we got. So there's a time function, but it's not in
terms of n, just we got a constant value. Now here, whatever the complexity in the statement
may be, how lengthy the statement will be, we say that it takes one unit of time.
Let us assume instead of this statement, I have some statement saying x assign five into
a plus six into b, if this is the statement written in an algorithm.
Then for this also we say it takes one unit of time.
But really if you see when you convert into a program and finally when it gets converted into
machine code, then how many statements it will have for each multiplication?
Two statements. Then for addition one statement, the assignment one statement. So total four
statements will be there. But we don't want to go into that much detail, we don't want to see
how it's going to get converted into machine code, but simply we analyze and say each statement
takes one unit of time. Now suppose if you want to go into detail analysis like this,
you can go into detail. You can imagine up to the level of the machine code that's going to be
generated. It is just like suppose you want to travel to your friend's house in a car,
you don't have to think and you don't have to plan and analyze,
simply you can take a car or your bike, your vehicle and you can just start and
reach its place. Right, that's simple. If you want to land on Mars,
then simply you cannot take a satellite, simply you cannot take a rocket and launch it and
reach there. It's not easy. So you have to analyze and design and make a complete plan so
that your mission is successful. So that's it. Here you need to go into each and every minor
detail you have to take care of it. So it depends on your requirement. So if you want
to analyze into greater detail, then do it. So the point of view, we will be doing it at
basic level. At a very shallow level, this brief analysis we will do will not go into much
detail. But much detail analysis can also be done.
Next is space analysis. What are the variables used here? For a space, I'll write down the
variables. A is one parameter, B is also a parameter and temp is the local variable used.
So total how many variables? One, two and three. So there are three variables used.
So the space is constant again, it is just three, I got the answer as three.
So here it is also constant. So usually we represent them as order of one, constant means
order of one. And that's also order of one, means it is constant, one represents constant.
If it is three also we write one, if it is three thousand also we write one,
saying that it is constant, value is constant. So this is how each statement is taken as
one order of time and each variable is taken as one word. So these are
three words. Why we are saying words there, not bytes? We don't know. When we converted to a
program it may be an integer type or float type or double type that we don't know.
So that's why we say it is taking words.