Now next is frequency count method. We will take some algorithms and find out
how this method is useful for finding the time complexity of algorithms. This
algorithm is for finding sum of all the elements in an array. Here is an array.
Assume that there is an array of some elements. I have taken an array of
size 5 with some elements in it. So what is n? n is 5. So a is this array and n is
5. Now what this algorithm is doing? It is finding the sum of all the elements
in an array. Let us analyze the time taken by this algorithm. So how do we do
that? By using frequency count method. So the time taken by an algorithm can
be known by assigning one unit of time for each statement. And if any statement
is repeating for some number of times, the frequency of statement, the frequency
of execution of that statement will calculate and we find the time taken by
that algorithm. So here we have some statement. This is statement which is
repeating for some number of times. So we will find out its frequency and
that will give us the time taken by this algorithm. So let us see. So this is a
simple statement. So this takes one unit of time. And as this is C language code
followed by algorithm, this is C language code, in this one we know this will
execute for one time and this will repeat for n times. But this condition
will be checked for n plus 1 time. How? When n is 5, then first time i will be
0. 0 is less than n. When i is 1, 1 is less than n, i is 2, 2 is less than n,
i is 3, 3 is also less than n, 4 is also less than n, 5 is not less than n, so it will
be 0. So how many times i has changed? 5 times. Then how many times this
condition is checked? 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 times. 5 plus 1. 4 times it was true and
fifth time it was false. When it became 5, it was false, so it has stopped. So
this is executing for n plus 1 times. So we say that if you sum up this, this is
2n plus 2, but we write n plus 1. So it means we are bothered about this one only.
Right? We are bothered about only this one, we don't want to write about those
things. Usually it is written n plus 1 only, but if you observe it carefully
it is 2n plus 2, but we don't want to write the time taken by these two.
Right? As i said, we'll be doing it briefly. Then, whatever the statement is
there inside this loop, as this is repeating for n times, this statement will
also repeat for n times. So this is n times. So now we can understand that
whatever is written in a loop like this type of loop, the statement will
execute for n times. And the loop itself if you take, it will execute for n
plus 1 times. Then the last statement, it will execute for 1 time. Then what's
the time function? f of n is 2n plus 1, 2, 3. That's it. This is the time
function. Now what is the degree of that polynomial? It is a degree 1, it is
just n. So we say order of n. I'm calling it as order of, I'm not saying
big O or theta, we will learn it in some other video. Now, for now, I will say
order of n. Base complexity. See what are the variables used here? A is used,
n, s and i. A, m, s, i. The size of A is n words and all these are just one
word. So total is how much? n plus 3. So that space complexity is s of n is n
plus 3. Now this polynomial is also degree n. So we say, space complexity
we got it as order of n and the time complexity is also order of n. Now next
algorithm is for finding the sum of two matrices A and B are square matrices
of dimension n cross n, n cross n. For example, it is 3 cross 3, then these are
matrices or two dimensional arrays of size 3 by 3, dimensions are 3 by 3, assume
that. So n by n, they are n by n. Now here I have an algorithm for finding the
sum of two matrices. Let us find out the time complexity for this one.
Already we know this will take n plus 1 time. Now whatever is there inside this
loop will execute for n times. This is n, this is also n. Two lines are there, two
lines are there. Now what is this? Again this is a loop. So for this also, n plus 1, then again whatever is
there inside this one will execute for n times. That's it. Now what is the time
taken by this one? f of n is n square, n square, 2n square plus n and n, so 2n plus 1.
This is the time function for this algorithm. What is the degree, highest
degree? 2. So we don't write degree, we write n square, order of n square. So
we are writing the degree. We are not saying that this is equal to this one.
We are saying that degree of this polynomial is n square. That's all. This is the time
complexity. Let us take space complexity. What are the variables that
is having a, b, c? a, b and c. n, i, j. n, i, j. What are a, b, c? They are
two dimensional arrays, n cross n. n square, n square, n square. What are n, i, j? They
are scalar variables, simple variables. One word, one word, one word. So space
function is 3n square plus 3. Then, what is the degree? n square. So this is also n
square. Space complexity is also n square. So the time and the space
complexity of this algorithm is n square. How to find the time complexity? I have
shown it here. How to find the space complexity? I have shown it here. So for
few algorithms I may be showing, for any algorithm you can find out this
one by following this approach. Next algorithm is multiplication of two
matrices. You can see that there are three loops nested, one inside another,
one inside another. Let us find out the time. On this side I will write, this
will be little far away. So this side I will write, so you can see them. This
is n plus 1. Whatever is there inside will execute for n times. Every
statement n times. Then, again this is a loop. So this is n plus 1. Whatever is
there inside will execute for n times. So into n, into n, and into n. Then again
there is a loop. So this is n plus 1 times. Whatever is there inside will
execute for n times again. So as this statement is inside all three loops, so
this is going to execute for n cubed times. This is inside just these two
loops, these two loops. So this is executing for n square and these are
loops themselves. So that is n plus 1 and this is n square and this is n cubed. If you
finally write down the time function f of n will be equals to, see n cubed and
one more n cubed, 2n cubed plus, this is n square and this is n square and this is
one more n square. So 3n square plus, this is 1n and 2n. So 2n plus 1.
That's it. Now we got the degree of the polynomial as cube. So the time
function is order of n cube. It's order of n cube. Let us see space for this
one. Space complexity for this one. A, B and C. Yes, A, B and C. n, i, j, k. n, i, j and k.
This is a matrix. So n square, n square, n square and all these are 1, 1, 1. So this
space is 3n square plus 4. So this is order of n square. Time is order of n cube. Space is
order of n square. You can have a look at this whole thing. So that's it. So I
have shown you three different algorithms taking different amount of time. One was
order of n and n square and n cube. Next video you can watch the different
type of algorithms and also the method how to analyze them.