hi in this video we learn how to trace the recursive function and how to write
a recurrence relation and how to solve a recurrence relation so I am taking
one of the example then in the other videos you can find following examples
more examples will come in other videos let us start already I have an
algorithm or function here a C language function I have written you
call it as algorithm also test is a function which is taking n as input and
if n is greater than 0 it is printing the value and then it is calling itself
for n minus 1 so I will take some sample value and test it suppose I am
calling this function by passing 3 let us see what happens if I pass 3 test
3 3 is greater than 0 yes 3 is greater than 0 print 3 so it will print 3 then
call itself for 3 minus 1 that is 2 so call test 2 then for 2 again it's a
1 is greater than 0 so it's a recursive call again for this one as it
is greater than 0 it will print 1 and call itself for test 0 now when it is
0 0 is not greater than 0 so it will not call itself and it will stop
doesn't go further so this is a tracing tree for this particular function or
recursive function I have passed 3 so what is the time taken by this one so
let us see what it is doing and this call it is printing a value then
calling again printing a value and calling again printing a value and
calling again so the amount of work done is just printing value how many
times it is printing this is the major work done by this function
printing a value how many times it is doing three times it is doing as I
have passed three how many times it is calling itself as I have given
three it is calling itself for four times now what is the time taken for
printf it is just one unit of time just a single statement and simple
statement it is taking one unit of time if I say one unit of time then in
each call it is spending one unit of time that is printing and then calling
so one unit of time one unit of time so total how much time it has
taken three if I take number of calls then there are four that is three plus
one it means if I pass five then it will be five plus one calls and five is
the number of time it is will it will print so if I pass n then total
how many calls it will make it will make n plus one calls n plus one calls
and how many times printf is executed n times if I approximate the amount of
work done depends on the number of calls if I say like in the last call it
is not printing just ignore that and say that for every call it is printing
so the time depends on what it depends on the number of calls so how
many calls it will make for any n it will make n plus 1 calls so the time
function if I write f of n then it is n plus 1 then what is the time
complexity in notations its order of n I can use big O of n theta of n or
Omega of n anything I can write there this we have already discussed in
previous videos so that's it by a tracing tree I have found the time
complexity of this one you can also call it as a recursive tree or a tracing
tree or a recursive tree I have used now let us find out how to prepare a
recurrence relation for this function and how to solve that recurrence
relation now if any function or an algorithm is given to you you can
prepare a recurrence relation as follows like this I am showing you assume that
the time taken by this is f of n no usually for recurrence relation
function name is T that is T of n is used so I'll use the same thing so
instead of f of n I'll call it as T of n time taken by this algorithm is T
n or this function is T n then that T n will be equal to what the total
amount of time taken by this one so let us observe what is happening
inside condition is checked let us ignore condition inside that printf is
there one it will take one unit of time the next what is the next one it's
a recursive call it's the same thing how much time we mention for this T n
then what will be the time for this one T n minus 1 right now that's it so
what is the total time T n I said that the total time taken by this part of
an algorithm so that T n is equals to T n minus 1 plus 1 now you can ask me
why you have ignored condition say if I consider that condition also for one
time then it is just one condition so one time then I'll get two here if I
take two also then the result of this result of this expression will be same
only for the recurrence relation I'll get the same answer so if you have any
constant value you can simply make it as one and use it or if you can write
it as C also and use it constant or some a as a constant some constant also
you can write and use it so I prefer taking it as one so if you have more
than one then you can round it up to one only all right this is the way we
write a recurrence relation now let us write a recurrence relation T n is
equals to T n minus 1 plus 1 this one when when n is greater than 0 yes when
n is greater than 0 this is the time what happens if n is equals to 0 it's
not doing anything if n is equals to 0 so if n is equals to 0 it is not
doing anything shall I write 0 here no the time we don't write it 0 if it is
0 also it's a constant so we write it as 1 so I will take it as 1 or else
you can make it as C or A or K anything some constant you can write
there now let us solve this recurrence relation now let us solve this
recurrence relation by substitution method back substitution we will follow
let us take this this is T n is equals to T n minus 1 plus 1 we will solve this
one that is already solved it is 1 we have to solve this one now for solving
this I can know the answer for T n if I know what is T n minus 1 so what is
T n minus 1 what is this if I know I will use it here so I don't know T n
minus 1 but I know what is a T n T n is equals to T n minus 1 plus 1 yes
this is the one then what will be T n minus 1 so if this is n minus n and it
is changed to n minus 1 so this also n minus 1 so this becomes n minus 1
n minus 2 plus 1 okay since this is T n therefore T n minus 1 is this one
now substitute T n minus 1 in this equation so T n is equals to in
bracket I'll write this T n minus 1 so what I got T n minus 2 plus 1 and
plus 1 so this part I have substituted here at this place so I got this one
then this is T n is equals to T n minus 2 plus 2 1 plus 1 2 if I
substitute again then T n is equals to what will be T n minus 2 T n minus
3 plus 1 see this T n minus 2 will be equal to T n minus 3 plus 1 yes I have
substituted this portion here right at this place so I have written this then
plus 2 is as it is now if I solve this one again then T n is equals to T
n minus 3 plus 3 that's what I got so how many times I should do this see
when I got two times that is sufficient you can continue further and
I say that I am going to continue this how long for K times continue for
K times if I continue for K times what I get see if you observe when I
did for one time it was two next time it was three then it goes on so it will
be K so this will be T n is equals to T n minus K plus K so this is the
important one for me now I'll continue here what is the equation I
T n is equals to T n minus K plus K see it was T n minus 1 plus 1 substituted
I got T n minus 2 plus 2 substituted I got T n minus 3 plus 3 continued up to
K so T n minus K plus K this one so I said that I will stop at K came in
some steps after some steps I will stop after K steps K substitutions I will
stop now what is the smaller value I know I know n is equals to 0 if n is
equals to 0 I know it is 1 answer is 1 so here and the minus 1 was there so
minus 2 then 3 then 4 if you go on subtracting like this at one point it
becomes 0 so the my purpose was to substitute go on substitute and reach
till n equal to 0 so I assume that I have reached at 0 so I assume this n
minus K is 0 and assume this means I have reached till there when I say n
is in minus K is equals to 0 therefore n is equals to K then what this will be
this will be T n is equals to T n minus n plus n then T n is equals to what is
this T 0 plus n so this is what is the T 0 T 0 we already know it it is 1
plus n that's it it is solved what the answer I got you see 1 plus n is
the time so just now I have shown you how we can prepare a recursive tree and
find the time for that algorithm actually I made a tracing as well as
along with that recursive tree so there also I got n plus 1 calls here
also I am getting the answer as n plus 1 so I have prepared a recurrence
relation solve that recurrence relation and I got this answer and this is
again order of n see actually this belongs to a class linear class order of
n that is n so I can call it as theta of n that's it this is the first
recurrence relation so I will show you more and more recurrence relation so I
will take the program I will prepare the recurrence relation and I will
solve it so continue watching rest of the videos