hello friends this is the next video on recurrence relation and the type of
recurrence relation is a decreasing function so already I have made one
video on recurrence relation or this is the second video see the title I have
given as recurrence relation decreasing function so one two three so
you can see all those functions so each functions is each function is
covered in a separate video now here I have a function it's a recursive
function when n is passed it is calling itself for n minus 1 then inside this
there is a loop for loop is there let us find out what's the time so for
this I will say this takes tn time then how much time this loop takes so I
try to take details this condition takes one unit of time and this for we have
been writing n plus 1 and whatever is there inside will execute for n times
then what about this statement this will execute for tn minus 1 time then
what is the recurrence relation if I write this one then tn is equals to
sum of all these so tn is equals to tn minus 1 plus 2n plus 2 this what
the recurrence relation I got but if I take it in this form it will not be
easy for me to solve it so this part of a relation we have to take a
asymptotic notation of that one means I should round round it up I
should not take 2n plus 2 so what is the notation for that it is big O of n
or theta of n also I can say it belongs to a linear class degree 1 so
that I can frame it as tn is equals to tn minus 1 plus n
instead of writing 2n plus 2 I can simply write n now this is the
recurrence relation see tn is equals to tn minus 1 plus n for n greater than 0
if it is greater than 0 and when n is equals to 0 what it is doing it is
doing nothing so I can say some constant or I will call it as 1 for
instead of constant I am writing it as 1 right or you can take C or anything
there so that's it so here we have learned how to prepare a recurrence
relation from a given algorithm or a function now this recurrence relation I
will solve it using recursion tree tn tn it is taking n amount of time this one
loop is taking n amount of time and also it is calling itself tn minus 1
then what about this step see that is printing n times so I have not
written print here I am saying that that statement is taking n times so I
wrote just time I'm not tracing it I am preparing a tree now this will be n
minus 1 and again it will call itself n minus 2 then this will be n minus 2
times this loop will repeat because now the value passed is n minus 2 and this
will be tn minus 3 continue if I continue like this then where it will
stop this n will reduce by 1 every time and it reach till 0 why because we
know the value of n is equals to 0 when n is equals to 0 answer is 1 so
that is the smallest value that we know so we say that it is reducing up to
t2 that time it will print 2 times and t1 and for t1 it will print that loop
will run for one time and this is t0 for t0 it does nothing that's it so
what is the amount of time taken here see if you compare this one with
the previous example in the previous video you can find that printf was
there so I was printing the value but no I am not printing the value I am
saying that this statement will take an amount of time because it is printing
n values instead of writing all n values I am just writing time now let
us find out the time how much time it is taking in this step n then the
what about this step n minus 1 time and then call so n minus 1 time and
this call is there so this call is taking how much time n minus 2 and then
n minus 3 so this will take how much time n minus 3 goes on this will take
how much time 2 and 1 then 0 if I sum up all these things then it will be
0 plus 1 plus 2 plus from here I am adding then goes on to n minus 1 plus n
what is this n into n plus 1 by 2 so the total time here see the time for this
one is n plus this time how much is this time n minus 1 plus this time so I
have added all of them so the total time is n into n plus 1 by 2 so tn we
got the answer as n into n plus 1 by 2 and this is n square now write theta we
go whatever it is it is n square so the time taken by this algorithm is n
square this is using tree method I have solved this right so see by practicing
you get the idea you don't have to elaborate it this much quickly you can
get the jump on to the answer so just you need to practice few functions
and recurrence relations and get the answer then you can directly give the
answer you don't have to solve all these huh when you are writing a theory
examination where you have to write essay type questions there you may have
to write on all these steps and then prove that it is n square if it is
objective type question direct answer you need so there is a method to know
the direct answer also we will be looking at this in coming videos now I
will show you another method that is back substitution or induction method so
that is back substitution by substitution we will solve this one so
I'll remove this and I will solve just recurrence relation now let us solve
this one tn is equals to tn minus 1 plus n I can move this one if I can
find out this so what is this since tn is equals to tn minus 1 plus n therefore
what a tn minus 1 will be tn minus 2 plus n minus 1 isn't it see n in case
of n in place of n n minus 1 so in place of n n minus 1 already minus 1
is there so n minus 2 then plus in place of n n minus 1 now I know this one
so instead of n minus 1 I can take this and substitute it here or this
becomes tn is equals to what is this tn minus 2 plus n minus 1 plus n as it
is if I open the brackets tn is equals to tn minus 2 plus n minus 1 and n
remember one thing whenever you are solving this one don't add it becomes
2 n minus 1 if it becomes 2 n minus 1 it will be difficult for you to find
out a formula for this one or a single expression for this sequence actually we
will be getting a sequence so based on that sequence we have to prepare a
formula if you add you'll be getting just a single one or two terms so from
that we cannot figure out the formula so better avoid adding these terms so if
this was the starting equation now after first substitution this is the second
equation I got now further I will substitute I need to know the value of
this so here only I will continue so what if I write n as n minus 2
instead of n if I write n minus 2 then this will be n minus 3 plus n minus 2
instead of n it is n minus 2 instead of n minus 2 sorry n minus 1 n minus 2
minus 1 so n minus 3 and this n minus 2 directly so in place of in this
equation only the first one only I have just kept n minus 1 in place of n
so you got this one so this part I will substitute it here so what I get
tn is equals to in brackets tn minus 3 plus n minus 2 plus outside n
minus 1 plus n open this one tn is equals to tn minus 3 plus n minus 2
plus n minus 1 plus n this is the third equation see after doing it for two
times then you can come on go to k steps and then you can get the formula
this is the method followed in induction right so we are substituting
the value so induction or substitution whatever you call it so I have done it
for two times now from this I can observe and say if I do it for k times
what will happen see when first equation it was n minus 1 and n this
was second equation n minus 2 and then n minus 1 and n two terms n minus
3 n minus 2 then 1 then n if I do it for k times what happens I'll use this
part yes if I continue this for k times let us see what I'll get tn is
equals to tn minus k instead of n minus 3 I am writing n minus k plus n
minus 2 this was 3 so it will be 2 1 less than this one so if this is a k
then this will be n minus k minus 1 this was 3 so that is 2 the next will
be n minus k minus 2 and goes on to n minus 1 and n so this is the fourth
one I got right this is the fourth one this is up to k now I assume that I
have reached till n minus k so I assume that I have reached till 0 and is 0 so
assume n minus k this one has became 0 therefore n is equals to k now
in place of k if I substitute n in this one let us see what I get tn is equals
to this one tn minus n plus n minus I'll open this so this becomes minus
n plus 1 so instead of k I am writing n and then I am opening the
ragged plus n minus n plus 2 then goes on last terms will be n minus 1 plus n
these two last terms as it is there is no k here now simplified further tn is
equals to t0 plus this nn gets cancelled 1 plus nn gets cancelled 2 so it means I
can figure out the next term is a 3 yes it is a 3 then goes on up to what
n minus 1 plus n that's it so what is this I got what is this I got this
is sum of first and natural numbers then tn is equals to t0 is what 1 plus
this is n into n plus 1 by 2 that's it if you compare the three method
there also I got n into n plus 1 by 2 but here I got one extra because this
is giving me calls number of calls actually so plus 1 call extra anyway
almost at the same thing so what is this this is theta of n square theta of
n square that's it I have solved this second one by using recursive tree
method as well as by substitution method and we got the same answer it's
order of n square so in this video we have learned how to write a
recurrence relation for any algorithm or a function then how to solve that
recurrence relation to get the answer so we saw two different methods
for solving it this useful for understanding the procedure how to solve
it and also useful for that is theory exams right but for objective type
questions you should know directly how to get the answer that will be
learning in next videos